<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached Feb. 2, 1689/90 with an addition of what was further designed on that subject / by Richard Pearson ...</title>
            <author>Pearson, Richard, d. 1734.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53908</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38163</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17198146</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17198146</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106193</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53908)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106193)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1621:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached Feb. 2, 1689/90 with an addition of what was further designed on that subject / by Richard Pearson ...</title>
                  <author>Pearson, Richard, d. 1734.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 41 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Redmayne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 41.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans II, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106193:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106193:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED Feb. 2. 1689/90. WITH An Addition of what was further deſigned on that Subject.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD PEARSON,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Michael Crooked-lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Tenere non potes, potes non perdere.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Redmayne.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106193:2"/>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe was preached only to <hi>pag. 17.</hi> the further Proſecution and Continuance of it (which you are here alſo preſented with) being interrupted through ſome Circumſtances which need not be now repeated. God Almighty grant that the Whole may find Succeſs with the <hi>Reader,</hi> anſwerable to the ſincere Intentions of the <hi>Author.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106193:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ROM. II. XXI.</bibl>
               <q>Thou therefore which teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS whole Chapter conſiſts moſtly of a ſevere Invective againſt the ſeducing Teachers of the <hi>Gnoſtick</hi> Sect, who though to avoid Perſecution, and to keep themſelves in a whole Skin, they baſely temporized and ſided, as they ſaw Occaſion, with each of thoſe Three diſagreeing Parties, were yet indeed themſelves neither Sincere Chriſtians, nor Honeſt Jews, nor Good Pagans. And though they vaunted themſelves for the only Knowing, and moſt Profound Doctors, yet their Lives were no other than a manifeſt Contradiction even to their own Doctrins; whileſt they both practiſed and freely allowed the ſame Things in themſelves, for which they moſt ſharply Condemned others. A thing ſo extremely Unnatural and Ridiculous, that the Apoſtle here in my Text, Appeals to their Conſciences, and is willing, even in their own Caſe, to make themſelves the Judges of the monſtrous Folly and Abſurdity of ſuch Proceedings.—<hi>Thou therefore which teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106193:3"/>
In Diſcourſing of which more than Self-anſwering Queſtion, I ſhall follow this Method; and obſerve,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That they who undertake to be publick Teachers and Inſtructors are indiſpenſably bound, never to deliver any Doctrin unto others, but ſuch only, both the Truth of which they do firſt moſt firmly believe, and are ready alſo, in ſpite of the utmoſt Hazards to put in practice their own ſelves: And that to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily affected, or diſpoſed is monſtrouſly Abſurd and Unnatural, moſt Shameful and Abominable.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That notwithſtanding this, and as Abſurd as it is, yet this is ſo far from being impoſſible, or any new Thing, that ſcarce any Thing is, or has been more common, almoſt in all Ages of the World, than inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſuch Perſons, whoſe Lives and Practice have been a flat Contradiction to their own Doctrins.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall conſider ſome of the great Evils and miſchievous Effects upon others, that are too naturally conſequent from the Conſideration of a multitude of ſuch Offenders.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſhall offer to you ſome proper Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Advice, by way of Antidote or Remedy againſt the Poyſon, and Infection of ſuch moſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Examples.</p>
            <p>Firſt I am to ſhew, That they who undertake to be publick Teachers and Inſtructors are indiſpenſably bound, never to deliver any Doctrin unto others, but ſuch only, both the Truth of which they do firſt moſt firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe, and are ready alſo, in ſpite of the utmoſt Hazards to put in practice their own ſelves: And that to be contrarily affected, or diſpoſed is mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106193:3"/>
Abſurd and Unnatural, moſt Shameful and Abominable.</p>
            <p>'Tis agreeable to the courſe of Nature, as well as the Rules of Chriſtian Simplicity; and ſuch for which we have our Bleſſed Saviour's own Example, That we ſhould firſt do our Duty our ſelves before we preſume to teach others. He who Preaches experimentally, and not meerly from his Head, but what comes from his very Heart and Life; nothing but what he himſelf verily believes and practifeth, ſuch a one will far more effectually work upon his Hearers; who well perceiving that the Man himſelf is in good earneſt, will eaſily be moved, by what he ſays, to the love of Vertue, and the practice of their Duty; as powerfully encouraged to the ſame, by the moſt evident Demonſtration both of the Neceſſity, Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and Poſſibility of the Thing, from the very Example of him who exhorts thereto. And how ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable is the Speech of ſuch a one, whoſe Heart, and Tongue, and Hand, (Men know) do mutually agree and go together? And how apt are all tolerably well diſpoſed Perſons to hang upon the Lips of ſuch a one? Whilſt what he ſays has quite another kind of Reliſh and Succeſs, than the very ſelf-ſame Words would have, if delivered to them by any other Perſon not ſo qualified: From whoſe Mouth, perhaps, they would have no other Effect upon them, than an eloquent Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion repeated by a Parrot; which could ſerve only to move Laughter. There is ſcarce any Object more Shameful or Abſurd, than a Perſon altogether rude and unpractiſed in the particular Art, or Science, which he publickly profeſſeth. He appears ridiculous in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all, and every Man is apt to treat ſuch a one with deſerved Contempt and Scorn. And by how
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106193:4"/>
much any Profeſſion happens to be in it ſelf the more generally uſeful and beneficial, by ſo much the more ridiculous ſtill does that Man render himſelf, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Skill or Practice therein, ſets up for a Maſter; and having never ſufficiently learnt himſelf, does yet take upon him to teach the ſame to others. But of all others, an immoral Philoſopher, and much more a vicious Chriſtian Divine, who Preaches one Thing to others, and himſelf Acts the quite contrary to it, is certainly the moſt fulſom Contradiction, and abſurd Spectacle in the whole World. So that, in this caſe, the Poet ſpoke the common Senſe of all Mankind, when he ſaid; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I abominate ſuch a Teacher, as has not yet taught himſelf.</hi> That of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaz</hi> to <hi>Job,</hi> had it been a true one, would indeed have been a very ſhameful Accuſation, Job 4. 3, 4, 5. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, thou haſt inſtructed many, and thou haſt ſtrengthned the weak Hands. Thy Words have upholden him that was falling, and thou haſt ſtrengthned the feeble Knees. But now it is come upon thee, and thou fainteſt; it toucheth thee, and thou art troubled.</hi> Nor indeed can any one, who is to correct the Manners of others, and pretends to be a Spiritual Doctor, have a more ſharp and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochful Reflexion caſt upon him, than the juſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of that Proverb in the Goſpel; <hi>Phyſician, heal thy ſelf.</hi> To hear Vice correct Sin; one who is himſelf in actual Rebellion, Preach up to others Loyalty and Obedience; to behold a practical Atheiſt, or a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched Epicure, reading to others a ſerious Lecture of Conſcience, or a Homily of Mortification and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyal, are certainly Things naturally apt to make a Man's Blood boyl within him, and his Breaſt to ſwell again, with a moſt juſt Indignation, at the intollerable
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106193:4"/>
Pride and Injuſtice, at the extreme Folly, Vanity, and moſt Damnable Hypocriſie of ſuch a Monſter. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, of all theſe, and of ſeveral other deteſtable Vices and Follies, there is always in every ſuch Perſon a moſt accurſed Complication.</p>
            <p>For Firſt, How ſtrangely unjuſt is it for a Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal to preſcribe ſuch Rules and Abſtinences, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to impoſe ſuch Shackles and Reſtraints upon others, as he can by no means endure to be concluded by his own ſelf? This is, in him at leaſt, no other than a manifeſt Uſurpation upon the ſuppoſed Liberties of his Fellow-creaturrs, and looks as if his deſign there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were only to monopolize and ingroſs Vice, and that he would not have others to offend, meerly to gain a larger Field for his own Luſt; and for fear he ſhould not otherwiſe have room enough to Sin himſelf. Again, what can be more Proud, Vain and Arrogant, than a behaviour that argues as if ſuch Men thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Creatures meerly deſigned to dictate to the reſt of Mankind? Or, as if by aſcending up into the Pulpit, they were withal ſo far Elevated above the Condition of their Hearers, as to be wholly exempt from all thoſe common Obligations of Men and Chriſtians: Or that their Souls were quite of another Make, and might be made happy upon far eaſier Terms, and by quite diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Methods, than thoſe of other Morals.</p>
            <p>Nor are ſuch Monſters leſs full of the moſt abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Hypocriſie. For, to be ſure, they who make it ſo their buſineſs, to inform others what they are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and do, would, by their ſo doing, fain ſeem them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves both to believe, and to be very ready alſo to practiſe their own Duty. They would be thought
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106193:5"/>
likewiſe to have their Hearts glowing hot with Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for other Mens Souls, and full of Zeal for God's Glory. Whereas, alas! they are meer Inſidels and Painted Sepulchres, and there is really nothing of all this in them. For all Charity begins at home; and no Man can Love another more than he does himſelf: So that he who is ſo negligent of himſelf, as to be wholly regardleſs of his own Souls welfare, can have no true regard for that of his Neighbour. And therefore, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all their Profane Eloquence and Religious Cant (for how True and Orthodox ſoever it may be in it ſelf, to ſuch Men themſelves it is no better) after all is done, let them pretend what they will, 'Tis not Charity or true Zeal that puts them upon the Performance, but ſome other baſe and much inferior Motive; which can be nothing elſe but either a deſire of filthy Lucre, or a principle of Ambition and Vain-glory.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, The Proceeding of thoſe who Preach well, and yet Live ill, is moſt ridiculouſly Fooliſh and Abſurd, and their Condition extremely Miſerable and Deſperate, upon many accounts and reaſons.</p>
            <p>For Firſt, Suppoſe ſuch Men could indeed have Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity enough to deſign therein any thing of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours welfare: (as I have ſhewn they cannot) Yet what reaſon have they to expect, that any thing they ſay, ſhould ever prove Succeſsful to that purpoſe, or tend in the concluſion to any thing elſe but their own Reproch? For who, I pray, would ever be perſwaded by that Man, who, after he has done Preaching ſhould plainly tell his Auditors, That he himſelf did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief one Word of what he had delivered to them? But now every Man, whoſe habit and courſe of Life is a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106193:5"/>
manifeſt contradiction to his own Doctrin, does, in effect, ſay as much as this comes to. Several of the Antient Emperors of <hi>China</hi> were ſo weak, as to believe a ſort of Phyſicians, who made it their buſineſs to ſtudy, and ever and anon pretended to have found out an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to make them become Immortal here; but ſhould any one of thoſe Juglers, when he himſelf lay juſt a Dying, have affirmed, though with never ſo much confidence, That he had indeed found out Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, but would not diſcover it, unleſs the Emperor would firſt ſetle ſuch a certain Eſtate upon the Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer's Children: I ſuppoſe, in this caſe, that none of them could have been ſo Fooliſh, as to credit the Aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veration; but muſt needs have ſeen through the ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſneſs of the Impoſture: In that had the Man really found out any ſuch Matter, he would certainly have firſt made uſe of it himſelf to prevent his own Death. So thoſe Perſons do enough perfectly to diſcredit their own Doctrin, who tell other Men, that the practice of ſuch and ſuch Vertues, is the only way to be happy here, and to obtain eternal Life hereafter; whilſt yet they notoriouſly neglect to practiſe the ſame themſelves. And, indeed, this Doctrin could not reaſonably have been believed, even from our Saviour himſelf had he himſelf lived ill. But yet here now I would not be ſo underſtood, as if I affirmed, that a bad Man can never be inſtrumental towards the Converſion of others; (for the ſame Motives, which for want of belief, or conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, prevail not upon himſelf, may yet from his Mouth be Succeſsful upon others; and God does ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo bleſs his own Word, though conveighed through ſuch impure Conduit-pipes, as to render it effectual) but my meaning is only this; That the quite
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106193:6"/>
contrary practice of the Preacher does very much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit the beſt Doctrin, and is ſuch a very great diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thereto, that, conſidering how the generality of Men ſtand affected, it does but ſeldom prove Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful; nor can Men well Credit or Embrace what ſuch a one ſays, meerly upon the ſcore of his own Authority. And though ſuch Men do happen to perſwade ſome, yet</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the mean time, They muſt needs upon other accounts, make their Profeſſion become extremely Difficult and Unpleaſant to themſelves. For every thing that is Forced and Unnatural is always ſo: But what can be more Unnatural, than to Force their Heads to be almoſt continually taken up with ſuch matters, as their Hearts are not at all affected with, but have really the greateſt averſion to? To which I may alſo add, whilſt they are Meditating what to ſay to others, how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible it is for them to avoid being ever and anon tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with the ſevere Stings and Laſhes of their own accuſing Conſcience. To ſay nothing, how their Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Forces them to provoke others, to be continually Scoffing at, and Reviling them with their own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins; whilſt all their Exhortations and Reproofs &amp; naturally recoyl upon themſelves, and are made to fly in their own Faces, and turned into ſo many bitter Satyrs againſt their own ſelves. There being nothing more true than that of <hi>Seneca,</hi> who pronounceth concerning ſuch Philoſophers, as inſtruct others well, but themſelves live ill; <hi>Ad ſuum ipſorum eſſe convitium diſertos, That they are Eloquent only to their own Reproch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Condition of ſuch Perſons is very De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate, and they muſt needs be extremely hardned againſt Repentance, as well by their having got a habit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106193:6"/>
to contemn all the Holy Directions, and by their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo frequently reſiſted and deſpiſed all thoſe Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Motives and Conſiderations, which they have made it their Trade to ſuggeſt to others: As alſo becauſe their Pride of Heart, in being profeſſed Teachers, makes them wholly Deaf to the Pious Exhortations and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances, and perfect Proof againſt all the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Rebukes of others; whilſt any thing of this Nature is uſually rejected by them with the higheſt Contempt and Scorn. Juſt as the Phareſaick Doctors treated the poor Man in the Goſpel—<hi>Thou wert altogether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and born in Sin, and doeſt thou preſume to teach us?</hi> John 9. 34.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Another great Miſery is, That ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons cannot (in all probability) long continue to preach True and Orthodox Doctrin unto others, but (as moſt other Hereticks have been moved to do, upon this very ſcore) will find themſelves forced, at laſt, to change the Truth they have all along aſſerted, for ſome vile Lie or other, that may better agree with their own vile Luſt. And this, as well the better to avoid the Stings of their own Conſciences, as alſo hoping thereby to ſilence the Out-cries of others, who are apt to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually upbraiding them with the great abſurdity of living againſt what they Teach; though, at the ſame time, they fall into no leſs ridiculous a Contradiction; being forced to ſay one Thing to Day, and the quite contrary thereto the very next. And however, if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this prevails with ſuch a one to broach Error; yet if there happen any extraordinary Revolution, or ſuch an Alteration of publick Circumſtances, that his former found Doctrin may chance to coſt him dear, or prejudice him in his Worldly Intereſt, it is then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106193:7"/>
for him any longer to hold out; nor can he find in his Heart to eſpouſe a Perſecuted Truth, but is eaſily frighted into the moſt ſhameful Recantation, or Abjuration of all he had ſaid before.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Though ſuch a one could continue always to teach Truth only; yet whilſt he Acts quite contrary to his Preaching, all his own Sermons will be ſure to riſe up in Judgment againſt him, and ſerve only to give Sentence againſt himſelf, and plunge him into all the Shame and Miſery of Self-condemnation at the laſt Day; when it ſhall be ſaid to every one no better qualified—<hi>Out of thy own Mouth ſhalt thou be judged, thou wicked Servant. Thou art inexcuſable, O Man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt: For wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf, for thou that judgeſt doeſt the ſame things. And thinkeſt thou this, O Man, that judgeſt them who do ſuch things, and doeſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgment of God?</hi> Theſe now are ſome of the great Miſchiefs which theſe Wretches bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by thus taking God's Law into their Mouths: (for as to the Evils which they bring thereby upon other Men, I ſhall ſpeak of them hereafter under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Head) And in ſhort, there is ſo much Folly and Diſgrace, ſo much Miſery and Abſurdity attending the Circumſtances and Condition of the Perſons I am now deſcribing, that there is not the moſt ſordid Trade or Occupation you can think of (though ſo mean and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial, that 'tis not fit ſo much as to name it in this place) but 'twere both far more Happy and Honourable for a Man to be of it, rather than be an Infidel Divine, or Self-contradicting Preacher. And, indeed, did not ſad Experience teſtify the contrary, one would be tempted to think it a thing wholly impoſſible, that any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106193:7"/>
Creature ſhould ever find in his Heart to be guilty of ſuch Monſtrous abſurdity. But this now brings me to</p>
            <p>The Second general Thing I am to ſhew, <hi>viz.</hi> That notwithſtanding all this, and as Abſurd as it is, yet this is ſo far from being impoſſible, or any new Thing, that ſcarce any Thing is, or has been more common, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in all Ages of the World, than inſtances of ſuch Perſons, whoſe Lives and Practice has been a flat Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to their own Doctrin. The Heathen Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers made it their Profeſſion to inſtruct others in the Paths of Virtue; and yet how little ſome of them ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved their own Rules, and how groſsly defective ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of them were in their own Morals, is a Thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by moſt Writers of their ſeveral Times, and indeed too Evident and Notorious to need any Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate inſiſting on. For the Proof of this, a Man need go no farther than the witty <hi>Lucian,</hi> who ſufficiently Scoffs at, and Expoſes moſt of them upon this very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. And every one who has been the leaſt conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in Books, knows how full the Poetical Satyriſts are of the ſevereſt Invectives to this purpoſe. Nay <hi>Seneca</hi> himſelf, that moſt celebrated Philoſopher, could find reaſon to complain of ſeveral of the ſame Profeſſion in his time, <hi>Qui Philoſophiam Oſtentationem ſcientioe, non legem morum putant; hoc turpiores, quod in eo ipſo peccant, cujus magiſtri eſſe volunt, artemque vitoe profeſſi, delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quant in vitâ. Who take up the profeſſion of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy meerly as an occaſion to ſhew their Learning, rather than that they eſteem it neceſſary to ſquare their own Actions thereby; in this, ſo much the more abominable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they offend in that very thing of which they would fain be thought Maſters; and live ill themſelves, even
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106193:8"/>
whilſt they profeſs to teach others the Art of living well.</hi> Nor was the very Author of theſe Words himſelf alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether free from the ſevere Cenſure contained under them: Since, if we may Credit that excellent Hiſtorian <hi>Dio,</hi> the very ſame <hi>Seneca,</hi> who had written ſo much about the contempt of Riches, was guilty of the moſt horrible Extortion; excited <hi>Nero</hi> to the Murther of <hi>Agrippina, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as many, and thoſe Perſon moſt worthy of belief,</hi> relate, ſaith the ſame Writer. And ſtill, after he ſpoken ſo many great Things relating to the contempt of Death, when at laſt he was commanded to die, for having conſpired againſt that Tyrant, he ſhewed himſelf ſo much a Coward, and ſo Fearful to try the grand Experiment, that he was fain to perſwade (or rather force) his Wife <hi>Paulina</hi> to ſhew him the way to die, by firſt cutting her Veins with his own Hand; as the before mentioned Hiſtorian ſtill gives us the Account. But why do I ſpeak of poor Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then? When we find God himſelf ſo frequently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining in Holy Scripture, even concerning the Jewiſh Prieſts and Doctors, whoſe Lips ſhould have preſerved Knowledge, that they cauſed his People to err, by their ill Example. And how does our Bleſſed Saviour tax the Scribes and Doctors of the Law, <hi>For binding heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens upon others, and grievous to be born, whilſt they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves would not touch them ſo much as with one of their Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers?</hi> Matth. 23. 4. <hi>i. e.</hi> They did not ſo much as once think of practiſing thoſe Things, which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and preſcribed to others. <hi>How often does he inveigh againſt them for ſaying, and not doing? For pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to ſee, and to pull out the Mote in their Brothers Eye, whilſt a Beam was in their own?</hi> In ſhort, the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Occaſion of their obſerving ſuch Doctors, whoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106193:8"/>
Words and Actions, whoſe Speech and Lives agreed not, made it become an uſual Proverb among the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews concerning ſuch Perſons—<hi>Their Voice is the Voice of Jacob, but their Hands are the Hands of Eſau.</hi> So true is that of the Son of <hi>Syrach,</hi> Eccleſ. 37. 19. <hi>There is one that is Wiſe, and Teacheth many, and yet is unprofitable to himſelf.</hi> Nor ſhall we find the times of Chriſtianity to have been ſo happy, as to want Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of this kind. For though in the Age of the Apoſtles, and for ſome time after, as the common ſort of Chriſtians lived much better, ſo the Miniſters of the Goſpel did generally both believe, and live up to what themſelves taught others; yet in proceſs of time, and by degrees, the caſe began to be much altered; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at, and after the times of <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> Inſomuch that that Wiſe and Religious Emperor was often forced to remind many of the grave Biſhops themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Profeſſion, and roundly enough to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them for their Contentious and Ambitious Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; as <hi>Euſebius</hi> and others may inform us.</p>
            <p>And too many others well deſerved that ſevere Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which the Heathen Hiſtorian <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus</hi> (with no leſs Honour to the Chriſtian Religion than with Diſgrace, if juſtly applied, to the Perſon) paſſeth upon one of them; who ſpeaking of <hi>George of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That he did this and the other ill Thing, Profeſſionis ſuoe oblitus, quoe nihil niſi juſtum ſuadet &amp; lene,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Being forgetful of his Profeſſion, which dictates nothing but what is mild and righteous.</hi> And ſtill if we come home to our own Country, we may find the Pious and Learned <hi>Gildas</hi> ſadly complaining of the ſame Scandal, and attributing the fatal Exciſion of the Ancient <hi>Britans,</hi> and their being Over-run and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106193:9"/>
by the Pagan <hi>Saxons,</hi> chiefly to the Greedineſs and Ambition, and general Corruption of the then Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Paſtors of the Iſland; ſuch, he ſhews, was the notorious Repugnancy of their Actions to their own Doctrins which they taught others.</p>
            <p>It would be endleſs and invidious, as well as unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for me to deſcend to later Times: And I could heartily wiſh, that every Man were not furniſhed with too great a variety of Inſtances to this purpoſe, even within the compaſs of his own Obſervation. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude this unpleaſant Theam with this following Remark; (and I pray God avert the Omen, as to our own particulars) There is not a more fatal ſign of the approaching Ruin of any Church and Nation, than when the generality of her Spiritual Guides, do by their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe groſsly Contradict, and give the Lie to the Truths which they have conſtantly maintained: Which makes them ready for any Innovation, and uſually obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them, for their ſuppoſed Credit and Defence, at length publickly to change and renounce their former Right Principles alſo, and Orthodox Doctrins; both which are neceſſarily attended with ſuch ill conſequents upon other Men, as are of the moſt dreadful Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</p>
            <p>And ſo this brings me now to my</p>
            <p>Third general Head, <hi>viz.</hi> To conſider ſome of the great Evils and miſchievous Effects upon others, that are naturally conſequent upon the conſideration of a multitude of ſuch Offenders.</p>
            <p>And here now, as well for brevity ſake, as better order, I ſhall reduce what I have to ſay under theſe Three Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106193:9"/>
Firſt, The Evils relating to the Atheiſtical and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane. Secondly, To the Weak and Ignorant ſort of Chriſtians. And Thirdly, To thoſe who are ſincere and conſtant in the profeſſion of the Truth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As to thoſe who are already Atheiſtical and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane; this muſt needs tend very much to confirm and ſtrengthen them in their Wickedneſs and Infidelity; give them no ſmall occaſion of Joy and Triumph, and mightily encreaſe their Number. To Argue and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, does well in its place, and is both very uſeful and ceſſary. And it is eaſie enough, even at theſe Weapons, to baſle the ſtouteſt Atheiſt; but yet (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in another caſe) there is to be ſhewn a far more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way than this; and, when all is done, the moſt effectual expedient is not ſo much to Diſpute, as to Live down Atheiſm and to Confute it, by Holy Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Tis eaſie for the Preacher to ſilence the Profane Wit, and put him to a nonplus, by what he may ſay in the Pulpit: But 'tis what he does, when out of it, that muſt effectually convince him. Which, if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to be notoriouſly diſagreeable, this of it ſelf, the Atheiſt is apt to conclude, is a ſufficient Anſwer to all the former Arguments; ſince if the Preacher himſelf did really believe them, he could never find in his Heart (as he obſerves he does) ſo to live in the plain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of any of thoſe Commands, which he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges to have God for their Author. And I could tell you, to this purpoſe of certain Atheiſts, who in ſome relenting Fits a little before their Death, plainly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to their Friends, That even in the time of their higheſt Infidelity, the ſight of any Perſon, who they had reaſon to believe, did really live up to his own
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106193:10"/>
Preaching, did conſtantly ſtrike terror into their Minds, and was apt to put them into a fit of Trembling: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, on the contrary, nothing (they found) tended more to harden and confirm them in their Atheiſm and extravagant Courſes, than the obſervation of ſeveral Church-men, who ſhewed ſuch a Greedy and Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Temper, and lived after ſuch a manner, that they could not be thought to be in good earneſt, or to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve themſelves when they talk'd to others of the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity of Holineſs, Mortification and Self-denial; when they who in the Pulpit would ſeem Religion's main Champions, do yet ſhew themſelves meer Runna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadoes-in their Lives and Actions, then begin all the profeſſed Enemies thereof to Applaud and Hug them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they delight to fix and dwell upon the pleaſing Object; ſuch Perſons become their continual Theam, and Argument, both of Diſcourſe and Recreation; nor is there any other Spectacle ſo perfectly Reviving and Delicious to them. And accordingly all the Traps and Snares, and Temptations imaginable are commonly made uſe of, by Men of this Spirit, to bring in as many as every they can of the Sons of <hi>Lew</hi> to a Sinful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with them. In which, when they happen to be Succeſsful, they are apt with the greateſt extaſies of Joy and Triumph to cry out (like the great Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matician upon his new Diſcovery.) We have now found out the way to quiet and appeace our own Minds; and let theſe Black-coats, for the time to come, ſay what they pleaſe, their Doctrins or Reproofs ſhall never any more trouble or torment us. For ſince we ſee they can afford to act the very ſelf-ſame Things, from which they have made it their buſineſs to deter others, we may certainly enough conclude (ſay they) that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106193:10"/>
believe not what they Teach; but as to matters of Religion are perfectly of our Minds, and would be ſure as plainly to declare no leſs, did not their Trade and Intereſt hinder them. Thus if the major part of Spiritual Guides can be at any time induced to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, theſe Men readily conclude therefrom, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the reſt of the ſame Profeſſion. And as for thoſe who keep their Garments unſpotted, and continue in their Uprightneſs and Sincerity; the Atheiſt endeavours all he can to perſwade himſelf, that they are really no better than the reſt at bottom, only more ſecret and reſerved Sinners, and a ſort of more cunning and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure Hypocrites.</p>
            <p>So that Miniſters, by what they Act, do of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity either the moſt Good, of the moſt Miſchief to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of any other People in the whole World. And an Apoſtaſie in them either from the Faith, or good Manners, is always attended with a general Defection of others. Nor are Atheiſts and Infidels, and all the black Squadrons of the Prince of Darkneſs ſo much countenanced, or encouraged by any Thing to march on boldly in open Triumph, as by the Revolt and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of ſuch Men to their Party. And accordingly, you may obſerve, That as no where do Church Men Live more looſely, or are more Ambitious or Fond of the World, that in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> ſo no where are the People more generally Atheiſtical and Profane, than in thoſe very places. Nay, indeed, when in any other place, the main Body of the Clergy ſuffer themſelves to be hooked in, or engaged to act quite contrary but to any one Truth, which they have before conſtantly Profeſſed and Maintained; this of it ſelf is a mighty advantage to Irreligion, and Naturally makes all elſe they have, or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106193:11"/>
can aſſert fall into Diſcredit; whilſt they give thereby but too great occaſion to Men of thinking, that they ſay, or do nothing at all out of a true Principle of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: But that they may eaſily be induced to offend, alſo in any other particular, upon the like Tryal or Temptation ſo to do: Which will always be ſure in like manner to be excuſed, and termed by them a caſe of abſolute Neceſſity.</p>
            <p>And thus much now may ſuffice to ſhew how much the practice of Self-contradicting Preachers tends to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, rejoyce, and encreaſe the Number of Atheiſts.</p>
            <p>But then Secondly, As to the Weak and Ignorant ſort of Chriſtians, the conſideration of this creates many, and moſt dreadful Evils. For, either Firſt, It is apt to make them take up with a ſtupid and brutiſh Imitation, and content themſelves without any more a do, or farther ſcruple, ſecurely to follow the bad Examples of ſuch Teachers. And how ordinary is it to hear many ſimple and tollerably well meaning People after this manner Arguing with themſelves? It's very true, that if I were left to my ſelf, I ſhould be very apt to ſtartle at this, or that Action, and could hardly find in my Heart to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on it. But now when I ſee ſo many great and good Men, the famous Doctors of the Church, hetherto ſo generally renowned for their Piety and Learning, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely leading me the way, in the ſelf-ſame Thing; Why ſhould I poor Wretch, think my ſelf ſo much Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer or Better than theſe great Lights, as to be afraid to follow them? Or why ſhould I be ſo Fooliſh to ſcruple it? Eſpecially, ſince withal my compliance therewith does ſo evidently tend to my Secular Intereſt and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage? I cannot but confeſs indeed, That I have often heard many of the ſame Perſons heretofore ſeem moſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106193:11"/>
ſeverely to condemn the ſelf-ſame Action, as a Crime moſt Heinous and Abominable: But yet now, they tell me, that the different Circumſtances quite alter the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Caſe; and they bring themſelves off with ſeveral other nice diſtinctions. Which though, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, (dull Soul that I am) I cannot underſtand; yet they themſelves doubtleſs do, whoſe Learning is ſo much tranſcendent. However, ſince they who know ſo much and have done ſo well in other particulars, ſeem to be ſo well ſatisfied about the Lawfulneſs of this, as to venture their own Souls, Why ſhould not I likewiſe venture mine upon the ſame bottom?</p>
            <p>Thus weak Judgments are naturally apt to be led more by precedent than precept. And what <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerves of the wicked Man in general, is Emphatically true of the Perſons I am now deſcribing; <hi>They ſpeak with their Feet, and teach with their Fingers,</hi> Prov. 6. 13. And how many Thouſands of poor Souls, who might be for ever Happy, would they but take more ſafe Methods, continually run headlong upon their own Ruin, by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely relying upon the erroneous Examples of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired Teachers, in ſpite of all their former Doctrins to the contrary?</p>
            <p>Or Secondly, If notwithſtanding all the little Salvo's, falſe Colours, and Palliations that can be made uſe of by ſuch Spiritual Jugglers to amuſe them, ſome People hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be of ſuch natural good parts, or unprejudiced Underſtandings, as plainly to diſcover, both the hainous Nature of the matter of Fact, and the evident Repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy and Inconſiſtence between the practice thereof, and the former Principles and Doctrins of their preſent Teachers; then the notorious Prevarication and Inſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of thoſe Guides and Paſtors, whom they obſerve
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106193:12"/>
complying therewith, is apt to create ſuch a mighty Scandal and Offence in the Minds of ſuch Perſons, as to tempt them utterly to forſake the Church and Profeſſion they are of, (though in it ſelf the beſt and pureſt in the World) and to betake themſelves into the Tents of the Adverſaries on the one Hand, or the other, and to joyn Communion with any Hereticks or Schiſmaticks they ſhall moſt phancy. Among whom (they are apt to perſwade themſelves) that though they may not perhaps find ſo much Truth, yet they ſhall meet with much more Honeſty and Sincerity: Since, they think, they have always obſerved a far better Conſiſtency and Agreement between their Practice and Principles, than at preſent in the generality of thoſe, whoſe Communion they are therefore now tempted to forſake.</p>
            <p>Or, Laſtly, If ſome Mens better Experience and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the World happens ſo far to acquaint them likewiſe with the groſs Errour, Deceit, and Inſincerity, that is too generally in other Parties and Profeſſions, as that they are forced to deſpair of mending their Paſture, and as bad as they are at preſent, know not where to better themſelves by a removal; then preſently they are from hence tempted to run into down-right Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm and Libertiniſm, and to ſet down in a perfect Diſregard and Contempt of all Religion in general. And what more natural in this caſe, than for them after this manner to argue with themſelves: Since the ſeveral Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Guides, who pretend themſelves appointed to conduct us, cannot agree about the way themſelves, nor are at all conſiſtent in their Practice and Doctrin, either with others, or even with their own ſelves; Why ſhould we therefore any more trouble our Heads or Hearts about any thing of Religion? For do not theſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106193:12"/>
Men themſelves by their Practice, as good as tell us, that they do not believe there are any Rewards or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments to be expected hereafter? And why ſhould we therefore imagine, that there is either Right or Wrong, either Good or Evil in any Actions, any farther only than as the ſame may tend to our preſent Pleaſure, Honour, or Advantage here in the World, or to the contrary? Commend us therefore, for the time to come, to the moſt Excellent and Divine <hi>Hobs,</hi> whoſe ſeveral Golden Volumes, in our Judgments, well deſerve to be chained up, and ſupply the place both of the Bible, Homilies, and Book of Martyrs, and his Memory to be duely celebrated, as the only true Confeſſor, and Father of our Church. Such a fatal Influence now, and moſt ſad Effect as this, is ſuch Mens Practice too apt to have upon weaker Chriſtians and enough to ſtumble all others, but thoſe only, whoſe thorough Acquaintance with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and well grounded Experience both of the Truth and Happineſs of the ſame, had placed them above the force of ſuch Temptations, and ſufficiently ſecured them againſt the Scandal of ſuch Examples.</p>
            <p>But, yet Thirdly, Even as to thoſe who ſtill remain Sincere and Conſtant in the true Profeſſion, a Multitude of ſuch Apoſtatical Offenders muſt needs create to them extreme grief of Heart, and bring upon them many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Evils and hard Tryals. And though they, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, who are yet Strangers to the true Power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, may perhaps be apt to wonder, that I ſhould here rank their Grief upon this account in the very Firſt front of their ſevere Sufferings; yet they whoſe Hearts are inflamed with Chriſtian Charity towards their Brethren, and have a quick Senſe of the honour of Religion, and are endued with a true Zeal for God's Glory, will eaſily
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106193:13"/>
perceive that this is no ſuch ſlight matter. For if <hi>David</hi> was ſo highly concerned, that, as for his own Sins, he mingled his Drink with Weeping, ſo he uſed to ſend forth whole ſtreams of Tears for other Mens, Pſ. 119. 136 <hi>Rivers of Waters run down mine Eyes, becauſe Men keep not thy Law; If Iſaiah</hi> likewiſe grieved ſo much for the People, <hi>That he would have none ſo much as to attempt to comfort him,</hi> Iſ. 22. 4. If the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, That his Soul ſhould weep in ſecret Places for their Pride, and his Eyes weep ſore, and run down with Tears; Nay, if ſtill, as if all this were too little, he wiſhes for new Springs to ſupply the courſe of his Grief, and to keep the Current running, Jer. 9. 1. <hi>O that my Head were Waters, and mine Eyes a Fountain of Tears, that I might weep Day and Night,</hi> &amp;c. And all theſe did this only for the Sins of the Common People: Oh! what Rivers then, nay what whole Oceans of Tears will not a truely Devout Soul be ready to ſhed, to ſee thoſe who ſhould be the prime Directors and main Sheepherds of the Flock, cauſe others to ſtray and wander by their ill Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples? No Words certainly are ſufficient to expreſs, nor can any other Man imagine what Heart breaking Pangs, and higheſt accents of Sorrow this ſad conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration muſt needs create, but only the Soul it ſelf that feels the ſame. Such Grief as is almoſt inſupportable, and would be beyond all poſſibility of comfort, were it not (as I ſhall hereafter ſhew) ſomewhat alleviated by ſome other conſiderations. But ſtill, beſides this Grief of Heart it coſts them, it occaſions alſo many other hardſhips to come upon them.</p>
            <p>For, Firſt, All the Hatred and Contempt, all the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Slander, Obloquy and Scorn, all the Hardſhips, Inconveniences and Perſecutions, which the ſmaller
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106193:13"/>
number of thoſe who are Sincere, and ſtill remain True to their Principles, are uſually forced in ſuch caſes to ſuffer from the common Sort, for refuſing to ſwim with the Stream, and becauſe they cannot in Conſcience comply with the general practice; all theſe Evils, I ſay, are originally owing to the Multitude of their falſe and revolted Brethren of the ſame Order with them. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the countenance and encouragement of whoſe nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Examples, the reſt of their now Enemies would never, in all probability, have had either the Will or Power, either the Opportunity or Boldneſs, to caſt upon them ſuch Indignities and Affronts, and to treat them with ſuch very hard entertainments. Nay, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, however ſuch lapſed Doctors may, for ends beſt known to themſelves, for ſome time fain ſome Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſy and Civility towards their poor afflicted Brethren, from whom they have ſo ſhamefully departed, and may, perhaps, at firſt entertain a real compaſſion for the hard Circumſtances of their Condition; and cannot, for the preſent, ſo much as ſuſpect that ever they ſhall be worſe affected towards them: Yet this ſeldom laſts long, but they fall by degrees, firſt to a leſs Reſpect, then to a Coldneſs, and at laſt to an abſolute Hatred of their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Which alſo firſt diſcovers it ſelf in diſparaging Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage—A ſmall company of pitiful inconſiderable Men; a few ſelf-conceited, four, obſtinate Fellows, who muſt needs make themſelves Wiſe and Righteous over much, and more Conſciencious than all their bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Anon the very name and ſight of the Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Odious to them and intollerable, as giving occaſion to their Conſciences of upbrading them; ſo that they find themſelves obliged, in order to their more Tranquility, to endeavour far enough to remove ſuch troubleſome.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106193:14"/>
Eye-ſores: And accordingly enter into conſultation with thoſe in Wiſd. 2. 12. and following Verſes. <hi>Let us lie in wait for the Righteous: becauſe he is not for our turn, and he is clean contrary to our doings; he upbraideth us with our offending the Law—He was made to reprove our Thoughts. He is grievous unto us, even to behold.</hi> And thus they uſually proceed on, till at laſt they turn the moſt furious and implacable Enemies to them in the whole World; and if they have an opportunity become the Authours and Fomentors of the moſt ſevere Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution againſt them: As we are ſupplied with ſufficient Inſtances of this nature, both in the Arian and Donatiſt Biſhops and Paſtors, and other Primitive Apoſtates. And how cutting a thing now, think you, muſt it needs be to receive ſuch treatment from the Hands of thoſe very Perſons, who were formerly their intimate Companions and moſt familiar Friends? Who uſed both to enter into, and take ſweet Counſel in the Houſes of God together with them: But now are turned their mortal Foes, meerly becauſe they Honeſtly perſevere in the practice, as well as profeſſion of thoſe very Truths; which the others alſo no leſs conſtantly taught in the ſame Holy Places, and made a ſhift to practiſe too, till ſuch times as they found themſelves likely to be looſers, if they continued to do ſo any longer.</p>
            <p>Thus having ſhewn you ſome of the miſchievous Effects of ſuch ſcandalous Examples upon others; I now proceed to that which is indeed the moſt uſeful and neceſſary part of my Talk, and what I accordingly at firſt did chiefly deſign; <hi>viz.</hi> To offer to you ſome proper Conſiderations and Advice, by way of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote or Remedy againſt the poiſonous infection of ſuch Examples.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106193:14"/>
In the performance of which Task, I am in hopes to make both my ſelf and the well diſpoſed Reader ſome part of amends, for that former great grief of heart, without which (I'm confident) neither he nor I have been hitherto converſant in the foregoing ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations; on which, I profeſs I ſhould never once have entred, much leſs now troubled the World with them, had it not been meerly for the ſake of what enſues, and (as 'tis always neceſſary firſt to diſcover the cauſes, nature, and effects of a Diſtemper, in order to its Cure) wholly to make way for, and in order to the better ſucceſs of this my laſt both more pleaſing and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble undertaking. To which therefore I ſhall now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my ſelf, with all imaginable cheerfulneſs and Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity: as deeply mindful of that, excellent Rule of <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> It becomes not a good man to ſpend his time ſo much in complaints of athers fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as in endeavouring to correct, and preſcribe Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, Then this very conſideration of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monneſs of this evil, may it ſelf very well be made uſe of, as no contemptible Remedy or Antidote againſt the ſcandal of ſuch examples. And ſince, as I ſhewed before, this is ſo far from being any new thing; that ſcarce any thing is, or has been, more common almoſt in all Ages of the World, than inſtances of ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whoſe Lives and Practices have been a flat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to their own Doctrins; ſo much the leſs reaſon then haſt thou to take offence, from thy own particular Obſervation of the ſame frailties. For, in this Caſe, no temptation is ſuffered to befall thee, but ſuch as has been common alſo unto others before thee. All holy men have been (more or leſs) exerciſed with,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106193:15"/>
gone through, and nobly Conquer'd the ſame Tryals. No Age, or place affords not ſome ſuch Doctors, who act quite contrary to the Truths which they Teach others. And if the Obſervation of this were indeed a ſufficient reaſon to make men fall out with Religion and their Duty, there could then ſcarce ever have been in the whole World from the very beginning of it, ſo many Righteous Perſons as that ſmall number which would have ſaved <hi>Sodom;</hi> and Heaven muſt have been without People. So that whoever thou art, that from hence endeavoureſt to excuſe thy ſelf from Duty, and art reſolved never to commence Saint thy ſelf till thou canſt firſt ſee all Miniſters become ſuch; know this, that thou art ſure to continue both wicked and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for ever; and wouldſt no leſs certainly have been ſo, even though thou thy ſelf hadſt had the liberty of chuſing any other time, or place of the World, almoſt ever ſince the Creation of it.</p>
            <p>But ſtill you'll ſay, the extraordinary unhappineſs of ſome particular Ages, may perhaps enable a Man, to object farther after this manner, I confeſs indeed, that what you've ſaid is very true; and were they only ſome few inconſiderable Perſons whom I ſaw thus act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quite contrary to their own avowed Doctrins, this I could have made a ſhift to have born with, as being no more than what I ſhould in reaſon have expected, nor could I therefore have been ſo much offended there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at. But now that Caſe is quite different, and when I behold a very great multitude of ſuch offenders, nay, when I obſerve the far greater number of thoſe who have been generally accounted the moſt eminent for Piety as well as Learning, notoriouſly guilty of ſuch a Defection; What would you have me to ſay, or think
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106193:15"/>
of this matter? And how can I chuſe, but be moſt grievouſly ſtartled and offended at ſuch an amazing ſight, and monſtrous conjunction of examples?</p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer in the general, that when the Caſe really happens to be thus, (as ſometimes, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, though more rarely, it does) this is indeed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſhock an ordinary Faith, and greatly to ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the weaker ſort of Chriſtians in their Religion, and courſe of Duty; nay, perhaps, it may well prove one of the greateſt ſcandals and temptations, that even the moſt experienced and beſt reſolved Chriſtian can likely be exerciſed with: But yet when all is done (I ſhall ſhew) not ſuch as is ſo altogether inſuperable, but that by God's Grace, and the impartial uſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and a thorough conſideration of things, we may be able to overcome, and be gloriouſly triumphant over it. In order to which bleſſed end, I ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly conſider in the Objection three ſeveral things. The Piety, the Learning, and the Multitude of ſuch offenders.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Their ſuppoſed Piety and Holineſs. In judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which you may conſider, how very liable men are to be deceived. For all is not preſently Gold that gliſters; and 'tis very poſſible that they whom thou ſo admiredſt for their Piety, were all along from the very beginning, no better then mere Hypocrites. Since even ſuch many times are prompted, through their Ambition and vain Glory, induſtriouſly to make a greater ſhew and glare, as to the external exerciſe of ſome Virtues, than thoſe modeſt and humble Souls, whoſe Hearts are really endued with a ſincere princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Holineſs and Religion. And though thou and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did well, and according to the Rules of Charity,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106193:16"/>
in believing them to be holy and ſincere, ſo long as in their Lives and Actions you could not diſcover any plain Arguments to the contrary; yet after once theſe evidently appear, and the rough hands of <hi>Eſau</hi> give the lye to the ſmooth voice of <hi>Jacob,</hi> the Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy of ſuch Teachers is then ſufficiently diſcovered, and they become ſelf-condemned, nor does any Charity oblige us any longer to conclude that they were truly Pious before, but rather mere Hypocrites; who would have long before alſo have ſhewn themſelves to have been no better, had they been aſſaulted with the ſame powerful temptations; which are now ſuffered to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iall them, on purpoſe to unmask them to the World; and that (as I ſhall hereafter ſhew) for the great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and the advantage of the Church of God, and that they who are approved may alſo be made more manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Or elſe, if we will needs ſuppoſe ſuch Teachers to have been formerly truly Pious and Sincere, yet we may well credit our own Eyes, and ſafely conclude, that they are now ceaſed to be ſo. For certainly, 'tis poſſible for Men to fall from Grace. To be naturally and neceſſarily Good is the ſole priviledge of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; whilſt no Creature is naturally impeccable; nor has God made any ſort of Men any more indefectible, than infallible to their Underſtandings, as to their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; the Righteous may leave off to be Good, and do that which is Wicked and Abominable; and when he does ſo, all his former Righteouſneſs is to be no more remembred either by God, or Man. And when all is done, that of St. <hi>John</hi> is the only firm and laſting Rule, whereby we are to judge in theſe caſes; <hi>He, and he only who doeth Righteouſneſs is Righteous:</hi> And ſince even the beſt have ſometimes their failings, we are
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106193:16"/>
not to follow them any farther, or to be led by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of their Examples, but only whilſt we ſee them walking according to the Rules of God's holy Word: But when we behold them acting contrary thereto, to be ſo far from thinking this any licence for us to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, as on the contrary to be excited therefore to grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fear and caution, leſt we alſo offend in like manner.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to the Learning of ſuch Men you may conſider, That Knowledge does not always, or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily make Men Good; nor is it any new Thing in the World to ſee Men very Learned, and yet at the ſame time very Wicked. Nay indeed, in many caſes, Men could not Sin ſo againſt Conſcience, nor arrive at ſuch a Superlative degree in Wickedneſs, were they not firſt furniſhed with a more than ordinary ſhare of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Moreover, What more ordinary, and therefore what leſs ſtrange, than to ſee a great deal of Knowledge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Charity? Which yet when unaccompany'd with this, can ſerve only to puff Men up with Pride to make them extremely Reſtleſs and Ambitious, and become ſo much the more like Devils to themſelves and others.</p>
            <p>And where is the Man, who, unleſs he has mind to expoſe his own Ignorance, will not eaſily allow both <hi>Celſus, Porphyrius,</hi> and even <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate to have been Men of no ordinary degree of Learning? Nor can we deny very many, if not moſt, of the antient He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks to have been Perſons profoundly both Knowing and Eloquent. Nay there's one I could name, who might he be permitted to appear in a Pulpit, and 'twere conſiſtent with his Intereſt to deliver ſound Doctrin, would be able enough by his Learning and Eloquence, eaſily to put down all Men for well preaching; nor is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106193:17"/>
there the moſt accompliſh'd Doctor living, but muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign up his Chair even to the Devil, and allow him the precedency, if meer Knowledge were the only Thing to be regarded: And yet that grand Apoſtate, with all his Learning, became, and ſtill remains no leſs, but ſo much the more a Devil; nor do I know of any Man who is ſcandalized at him for ſo continuing.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it may help to hinder thy being over much offended at the bad Examples of ſuch revolted Teachers, when thou ſhalt obſerve, (as it always happens in ſuch caſes) that they themſelves with all their Learning, are not able to anſwer their own former Arguments, either for the Truth, or neceſſity of practiſing thoſe ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins, which they before delivered and maintained: But when they attempt any thing of this nature, they uſually do it ſo aukwardly and unhappily, and with ſuch an evident byaſs upon them, as may ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince any impartial conſiderer, That they themſelves give no credit to their own diſproofs; nor are at all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in what they ſay or write to the contrary of their firſt aſſertions. Whilſt their whole proceedure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly amounts to no leſs, in the Eyes of all judicious Obſervators, than if they ſhould make a plain Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion after this manner; ſuch a Doctrin was indeed once very true, when we firſt delivered it; and though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the ſame became, for ſome time very falſe, whilſt it was not for our intereſt to obſerve, or be guided by it; yet now our turn is ſerved, it is very true again, and will never be falſe any more, till ſuch time as it ſhall happen in like manner, to be for our preſent advantage, to have it thought ſo. Thus, when learned Men are forced, to play faſt and looſe after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and to fall into all the abſurdities of ſelf-contradiction,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106193:17"/>
whilſt they ſuffer themſelves to be wholly guided by Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular motives; all their latter feeble attempts to deſtroy and diſcredit, may very well ſerve (if rightly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) for the greater Eſtabliſhment and Confirmation of thoſe Truths, which they formerly maintained in their more calm and unprejudiced Temper. In ſhort, ſince it is ſo ordinary, Why ſhould it ſurprize you, or ſeem ſtrange to behold Men very Learned, and yet at the ſame time extreamly fond of the World? How many have there always been ſince the declining times of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity who have ſearched and ſtudied hard, and taken a great deal of pains to be skilful in the Scriptures, and knowing in the miſteries of Religion, not out of a love to Truth, or any right Intent to pleaſe God the better, but meerly that they might be applauded, and had in admiration by others or that they might grow rich by their Knowledge? The ingenious <hi>Picus Mirandula</hi> ſadly complains of this fordid Temper, as that fatal Diſeaſe with which ſome learned Men of his Age were grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly infected. <hi>Who could not believe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that any one ſtudied for Knowledge, out of any other deſign than ſuch filthy Lucre.</hi> And he ſpeaks of Two, with whom he himſelf had ſome acquaintance, the one of which (though reputed a learned Man) was not aſhamed to confeſs to him, That he could be heartily pleaſed to part with all his Knowledge, if he could ſell it for ſuch a ſum: And the other, That he had rather be a Horſe than what he was, if he could but have as much to live upon, as he deſired; when yet that Perſon (ſaith the ſame Author) had already enough in reaſon for any contented Mind.</p>
            <p>Now, ſince 'tis alas, but too common even for learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men to be of this ſordid Temper; Why ſhould you
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106193:18"/>
then be ſo much offended to behold ſuch Men, upon occaſion, ſelling their Learning, and the Truth, by unſaying and contradicting what they had before ſaid, and done rightly, when by their ſo doing, you plainly perceive them to get, or ſecure that very thing which they always priſed more, and for the ſake of which alone they at any time before put any value upon Truth or Knowledge? Thus, that of St. <hi>Paul, Demus hath forſaken us, having loved this preſent World,</hi> may be generally applied alſo to all other Apoſtates howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever learned.</p>
            <p>But I now proceed, in the Third place, to the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſuch Examples. Where, firſt, you may conſider that all things rightly weighed and accounted for, they are not really ſo very numerous, as is uſually pretended in ſuch caſes. For generally there are no more than Three or Four, or ſome ſuch number of cunning and deſigning Men who have made it all along their buſineſs to be very Popular, and hapning to be placed in higher Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions than ordinary, get thereby the advantage of look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing big, and of having their Learning and Integrity meaſured by the greatneſs of their preferments: Theſe Men commonly are the ſole Authors of ſuch revolts; whilſt moſt of the reſt of the ſame Cloth, without any ſufficient uſe of their own Reaſon, or due Conſideration, ſuffer themſelves to be wholly led and prevailed upon by the meer force of the others great Name and Authority, and the hopes of riſing higher by their means: being ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able when they come from them to give another any account, or ſo much as barely to recite thoſe Arguments, by which yet they pretend themſelves to have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. Now all theſe, (maugure their outward ſhape and habit) will certainly have too great an honour done
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106193:18"/>
them, if they be allowed to paſs ſo much as but for half men. They are to be lookt upon only as a ſequacious ſort of meer Animals, or rather indeed as ſo many ſeveral Cyphers which ſignify and ſtand for juſt nothing at all in themſelves, but ſerve only to ſhew how conſiderable a Figure the others make in the World, and how much value themſelves put on them, upon that account. So that you ſee, take but away all theſe, (as in all juſtice they ought to be ſubſtracted from the account) and there will be no great cauſe to brag of Multitude. And however, let even all theſe alſo go into the Tale, and help to make up the Dead weight; yet the total Sum of ſuch lapſed Teachers in any particular Age, or Place (which is the only matter of ſcandal I am now endeavouring to remove) would be found very inconſiderable, and juſt next to nothing, in compariſon of the far greater numbers of thoſe, who in all other Ages and Places, have ſtood firm and conſtant, to the very laſt, in the ſame right principles and practices, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the ſevereſt tryals and temptations to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Add but all theſe, I ſay, to the ſmaller Catalogue of thoſe ſurvivors, who ſtill tread in the ſame holy ſteps, (as all holy men whether living, or dead, are to be looked upon to belong to, and make up the ſame general Communion and Society) and then, what a glorious Army of Martyrs? what a noble Company of Confeſſors will you behold, for your comfort and encouragement? Enough, for number as well as quality, to dazle the Eyes, and confound the Hearts, of all thoſe, who may for the preſent happen to joyn hand in hand in wickedneſs, and endeavour to countenance and encourage one another therein, from the conſideration of their ſo much vaunted of Multitudes.</p>
            <p>But ſtill, ſuppoſe the far greater numbers were really on that ſide, on which they are pretended; yet what force or preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ought this conſideration to have upon any wiſe man's mind, who is reſolved to deal faithfully with his own Soul, and to be true to his own Spiritual Intereſt? Certainly, none at all; unleſs it could be firſt proved, That the major part of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, do always, in all particulars, neceſſarily determine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves according to the meaſures of Truth and Righteouſneſs. Than which (though I could heartily wiſh it were true) no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106193:19"/>
is more notoriouſly falſe, according to all Experience. For do we not find that the Prieſts and Scribes, and the whole Jewiſh Sanhedrim in general agreed together upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation even of our Bleſſed Saviour, whilſt <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathea</hi> was the only perſon we read of who conſented not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? And who knows not, what, and how many groſs errours, both in matters of Belief and Practice, were for ſeveral hundred years together, promoted and maintained in the Chriſtian World, by the far greater part of Doctors generally had in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation for their Piety as well as Learning; ſome few only in their ſeveral Ages, ſtill gain ſaying and withſtanding the ſame?</p>
            <p>So that Proteſtants, of all others, ought by no means, in any caſe of this nature, to admit of Arguments drawn from this Topick, the weakneſs of which upon other occaſions, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have ſo abundantly expoſed, and therefore moſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly exploded.</p>
            <p>In merely civil Affairs, indeed, there is ſome reaſon, that things ſhou'd be carried according to the majority of Votes; becauſe where there is the greateſt number, there is generally alſo on the ſame ſide, the greateſt force and intereſt, which is much to be conſidered in ſuch matters: But in a caſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or in matters of Right and Wrong, Truth and Falſhood, numbers are not at all to be regarded; nor does it behoove a man, to tell Heads, but only to weigh Arguments. Nay, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Multitude is ſo far from being always a good Argument of Truth, or of the Righteouſneſs of a cauſe, that conſidering the general frailty and corruption of man kind, it is rather to be lookt upon, as the quite contrary; and we have ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, at leaſt to ſuſpect (where the caſe is before any thing doubtful) that, that may be the wrong way, in which we behold moſt men walking; eſpecially when it happens to be very manifeſt, how much their ſecular Intereſt is alſo to be met with in the ſame paths. Beſides, we are aſſured from Chriſt himſelf. That his Flock is ſmall, in compariſon of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who are therefore called <hi>the World; That the many go in the broad, but wrong way; whilſt ſtraight is the Way, and narrow is the Gate that leadeth unto Life, and few there are that find it.</hi> And God himſelf forewarns us, that in any caſe, <hi>We follow not a Multitude to do evil.</hi> Moreover, we may remember for how
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106193:19"/>
long time together Gods Church conſiſted within the narrow compaſs of one ſmall Nation; and before that, how 'twas ſcarcely viſible any where elſe, ſave in the one Family of the Father of the faithful. Nay, in the time of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be reduced to a ſingle man, whilſt the whole World was turned Arrian: And though I doubt not, but that there were ſeveral others who believed rightly; yet that Biſhop was the only Perſon, who durſt at that time ſo openly appear for the Truth; and was often removed from his place, ſeverely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and baniſhed for doing ſo.</p>
            <p>Now, all this being well conſidered, what reaſon haſt thou, to be at any time ſcandalized at the fewneſs of thoſe who ſtand to their principles in the time of tryal? Or rather, why ſhould not thoſe few no leſs learned and far more pious perſons, whom thou well perceiveſt to be in good earneſt about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in that they perſiſt in the belief and practice of what themſelves have taught, even when it is quite contrary to their worldly Intereſt, and they meet with nothing but reproch and perſecution for ſo doing; why ſhould not the example of theſe few, I ſay, be far more powerful to confirm thee in the truth, than that of the other to ſcandalize thee out of it, eſpecially; when it ſhall happen to be very notorious, by what fordid motives they were prevailed upon, either to renounce their firſt principles, or groſsly contradict the ſame by their following practice; conſider likewiſe, that they who continue firm and conſtant, and help to make up the ſmall, but Bleſſed number, are not themſelves at all ſtaggred, but rather (in ſome reſpects) rejoyce and triumph at their very ſewneſs: And why then ſhouldſt thou be ready to take ſo much offence thereat? Or, ſince they are already ſo few, how canſt thou find in thy Heart, to make them ſtill fewer, by thine own revolt? Theſe conſiderations now may I hope, ſerve to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the uſual Objections, and prove a good Antidote againſt thoſe ſcandals which are apt to ariſe from the Obſervation of the ſuppoſed Picty, Learning, and far greater number of thoſe who are at any time, lapſed from the truth.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, As the moſt eſſectual Remedy againſt the poyſon of ſuch examples, endeavour above all things, ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſortify your Hearts with godly ſincerity; look that you
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106193:20"/>
eſpouſe right principles out of right ends, and be ſure you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form every Duty for God's ſake, and as in his preſence. For when once a firm Habit of rectified Intentions and ſingleneſs of Heart has (as certainly it will) enabled a Man thoroughly to reliſh Duty, and to <hi>Taſte, and ſee how good the Lord is,</hi> he will be ſure to experience ſuch unſpeakable Joy, ſolid Pleaſure and ſatisfaction therein, that he would not for the whole World part with it; and they muſt firſt perſuade him out of his very Senſes, as well as his Reaſon, who would prevail with him, to do any thing by which, he knows he muſt forfeit the ſame. So that after thus antidoted with Godly ſincerity, let other men, in whole ſholes together, or (if you pleaſe) in the moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected proceſſions, go to make ſhipwrack of their Faith, and of a good Conſcience; let thouſands daily fall on thy right hand, and ten thouſand on thy left, the Plague ſhall not come nigh thee, the Infection of ſuch examples ſhall never once touch thee.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let the matter of ſcandal be in it ſelf never ſo great, yet conſider, that, in ſuch caſes, God many times permits a powerful occaſion to be adminiſtred, whereby ſo many Doctors and of ſo great a name (though all along no better than cloſe Hypocrites) ſhould at laſt unmask themſelves and fall ſo foully, on purpoſe to try the ſtrength of thy Faith; to make thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Spectacle to Men and Angels; and that it may appear how ſincere and well-grounded thou art in the Truth, who canſt not be ſhaken out of thy Duty and Religion, by all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Winds of falſe Doctrin, or the greateſt Earth-quake of a general Apoſtaſie. Why ſhouldeſt thou therefore be ſo much troubled or offended at that, which (if it be not thine own fault) will certainly tend to the great encreaſe of thy Renown and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs? For the more difficult thy Tryal and Temptation, ſo much the more eminent and remarkable will be thy Vertue in the Conqueſt, ſo much the greater the Honour of the Triumph, and ſo much the more Glorious thy Reward and Happineſs hereafter.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It may very much help to abate thy Scandal, when thou ſhalt conſider the many and great benefits, which uſually redound to the Church of God in general, whilſt they who are approved, or the contrary, are hereby made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:106193:20"/>
For, Firſt, ſuch diſcovery does, for the time to come, more effectually ſecure pious Perſons from being any way miſled out of their Duties, by the corrupt examples or perſuaſions of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed Hypocrites. Familiar converſe with ill men is very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and infectious, and apt inſenſibly to taint, and make a man tread awry, even before he is aware. And when many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Hypocrites are mixed together in the ſame Comunion with the Faithful, and ſeem to worſhip God at the ſame Altar; good men are apt to ſuſpect no harm from them, but to give ear to their Inſinuations and Advices; whilſt falſe Friends are always, upon this very account, moſt dangerous to the Church, and the true Members of it in particular: But now when ſuch men have diſcovered and unmask'd themſelves by their open Apoſtaſie, every ſincere perſon is enabled to look upon them as down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Enemies, and is accordingly ſufficiently prepared and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidoted againſt their Poiſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, When ſincere perſons come once generally and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to know one another, (as by this means they always do) they then become hereby the better enabled, to love, value, and truſt, each other; and have a fitter opportunity moſt cloſely and ſecurely, to combine their ſeveral Prayers, Counſels, and pious Endeavours, for mutual edification, and the Churches welfare.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, When, by ſuch Lapſes, the Chaff is well ſifted and winowed from the Wheat, ſo that they who ſtill continue in their Integrity, and ſtand to their Principles, have ſufficiently diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves to be ſincere and hearty; then may that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, (howſoever greatly decreaſed in the numbers of its outward Members) upon good reaſon, conclude it ſelf in a more ſafe and hopeful Condition, than it was before; as more immediately entituled to God's favour and protection; and now, by ſuch purgation, become more ſtrong, ſound, and healthful, in its Conſtitution, is therefore far better qualified for a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous State.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The diſcovery and manifeſtation which ſuch Lapſes make, is of ſingular benefit to the Church of God, as it tends moſt effectually to ſecure them from that dangerous errour and folly, by which even many well-meaning men are ſometimes liable to be overtaken, whilſt they are too apt to forget, that their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106193:21"/>
Treaſures are conveighed to them, through the mediation of earthen Veſſels as the Inſtruments: By the experimental frailty of which, they are ſufficiently inſtructed, for the time to come, not to depend ſo much upon any man's meer Authority, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, howſoever had generally in repute, both for Piety and Learning; to call, or make no meer man on Earth the abſolute maſter of their Faith, nor to have mens perſons ſo in admiration: But to learn to eſteem of Teachers chiefly for their Works ſake. In ſhort, when they, who before were too apt to favour and follow ſlie Seducers, ſhall evidently perceive how groſsly they contradict themſelves, how foully they have fallen, and that they really mind nothing but the World; ſuch men are from hence, preſently moved to forſake them, and to betake themſelves to more ſincere Guides. So that God's faithful Miniſters, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding (as it ſometimes falls out) the weakneſs of their bodily preſence, or their leſs ſhare of Eloquence, become at laſt, by this means, to be more lov'd valu'd, and duly rely'd upon by their reſpective Flocks.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, When God ſees fit that ſuch a Church ſhall come afterwards to be well ſettled and compoſed again, that mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation which the former Lapſes and Revolts have made both of mens Integrity and Abilities, or of the contrary, muſt needs prove of admirable uſe; the better to direct thoſe, who are in Authority ſo to do, towards the choice of fit Spiritual Officers, and Governours, and to enable them to know, what particular perſons are to be rejected, and who moſt ſafely to be promoted to places of greateſt Truſt and Eminency in the Church: then which ſcarcely any thing can be of greater Conſequence or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance. And accordingly, they who either Lapſed from the Faith in the times of Perſecution, or were guilty of any heinous Crime, were hereupon, in the Primitive times for ever after held uncapable (though they did repent) of coming to any Office in the Church, or were excluded and depoſed there-from, if before they hapned to enjoy ſuch Dignity. Whilſt, on the contrary, no Perſons were thought ſo fit, to be promoted to Places Eccleſiaſtical, (though perhaps, at the ſame time, leſs eminent in Learning) as they who had manifeſted their Firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Integrity under ſuch Tryals. For the firſt of theſe, we may give credit to St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> whoſe words are theſe in his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106193:21"/>
50. Ep. to <hi>Boniface; Ut enim conſtitueretur in Eccleſiâ, ne quiſouam poſt alicujus criminis paenitentiam, clericatum accipiat,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That Conſtitution of the Church, by which it is provided, that they who have been guilty of any heinous Crime, ſhould never, even after their Repentance, be ſuffered to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, or return to the Office of a Miniſter, does not proceed from any deſpair of their Forgiveneſs, but only from a neceſſary rigour and ſtrictneſs of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi> By which (he ſaith) they more effectually conſulted both the ſafety and humility of ſuch Perſons; intimating likewiſe, a little afterwards, what he thought was the reaſon that induced the Ancients to make ſo ſevere a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. <hi>Experti, credo, aliquorum fictas paemtentias, per affectut as honorum potentias. Having experienced the counterfiet Repentances of ſame, meerly to attain to, or regain ſuch honourable Stations.</hi> Which they thought might far better be ſuppled, by thoſe whoſe approved conſtancy and fidelity might more ſecurely be relyed upon. And remarkable to this purpoſe is the Epiſtle of St <hi>Cyprian,</hi> concerning his having Ordained one <hi>Cilerinus,</hi> to be a Reader in the Church of <hi>Carthage;</hi> for this was an Office, in thoſe days, highly honourable This <hi>Cilerinus</hi> had ſhewn himſelf an approved Souldier of Chriſt, gloriouſſy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing over a long Impriſonment, and all the moſt exquiſite Torments. Concerning whom therefore the Holy Biſhop, writes to his Flock in theſe Words of Commendation. <hi>Hunc ad nos, fratres dilact ſſtini, cum tanta Domini dignatione venientem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This Man, moſt beloved Bretheren, coming to us with ſuch ſingular Approbation of our great Lord, and moſt Illyſtrous even according to the Teſtimony of his very Perſecutors, How can we more fitly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of, than by placing him in the Reading Desk, that is, upon the Tribunal of the Church, that ſo, by the advantage of a higher Place, become, according to his deſerved Honour, the more conſpicuous to the whole Congregation, be may read thoſe Precepts and that Goſpel of our Lord, which he does ſo faithfully and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly follow? Let that Voice of his, which has ſo manfully confeſſed Chriſt, be daily heard in the Repetition of thoſe holy Words, which our Lord himſelf has ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Nor is there any thing, in which a Confeſſour can be more profitable to the Brethren, than in this, that, whilſt the Goſpel is pronounced out of his Mouth, whoſoever hears the ſame, may be thereby invited, to imitate the Faith of the Reader.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am ſenſible I have made too long a Digreſſion. To return there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to what I more immediately deſigned. Since, in all theſe reſpects, the diſcovery of thoſe who are Sincere and Faithful, and who are not, is a thing ſo highly advantagious to the Church of God, How can we then ſuffer our ſelves to be ſo much troubled and offended at thoſe previous Lapſes and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volts, which tend to make ſo profitable a manifeſtation?</p>
            <p>I ſhall now mention but one Remedy more; and yet I know not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no it be ſo proper for me to do it, becauſe it is ſuch, as is not within the compaſs of their own reach or power to be furniſhed with who are ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to take the offence. But however, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>'s Providence as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it does) is pleaſed to adminiſter the ſame, it proves as efectual an Antidote againſt ſuch Scandal as any of the former. If any number of ſuch lapſed Perſons, could, upon better conſideration, be brought in due ſeaſon, publickly to acknowledge and confeſs their Errour, and the corrupt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106193:22"/>
which induced them thereto; and that whilſt they ſtill continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame Circumſtances and powerful Temptations, which firſt prevailed upon them to fall into it; this, above all, would mightily tend to ſatisfie the minds of weaker Chriſtians, and take off the former Scandal. And how thoud any thing of Fooliſh Shame, or Worldly Intereſt be able to hinder them from this performance? If they would but ſeriouſly conſider, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is, even for the preſent, more truly Honourable in the judgment of all Wiſe Men, than for them to do this, and withal call to mind that eternal Shame and Confuſion, which will be ſure to cover their Faces at the laſt Day, if now they do neglect it. Let that aſtoniſhing Queſtion of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour continually dwell upon their minds; <hi>What will it profit a Man to gain the whole World, and looſe his own Soul?</hi> Let them think how many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of poor Souls they muſt one Day anſwer for, who are like to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done for ever by their bad Examples; and let them alſo reflect, when they ſhall come (as very ſhortly they muſt) to lie upon a Death-bed, and all that either they have kept, or gotten by their ſhameful Prevarication muſt be parted with for ever; what an unſpeakable comfort it would then be for them to have the Witneſs of a good Conſcieece, and to be able to ſay, truly, with St. <hi>Paul, I am clear from the Blood of all Men.</hi> To conclude, I ſhall leave all ſuch revolted Teachers to conſider with themſelves how nearly they may be concerned in that Exhortation, as well as ſevere Threatning of Chriſt to the Angel, Biſhop or Paſtor, of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Rev. 2. 5. <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do the firſt works, or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and will remove thy Candleſtick out of his place, except thou repent.</hi> And thus I have done with the laſt general thing I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, <hi>viz.</hi> To offer to you ſome proper Conſiderations and Advice, by way of Antidote or Remedy, againſt the Poiſon and Infection of ſuch moſt Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Examples.</p>
            <p>And now, perhaps, ſome may expect from me (a Task which I as eaſily could, as I heartily wiſh I could not perform) that I ſhould ſtill deſcend to a particular Application of what I have hitherto delivered only in a more general way. But I deſire herein to be excuſed; not that I dare not, for if (all Circumſtances conſidered.) I could apprehend this to be ſuch, I thank God, I dare do any thing, that I think to be my Duty, whatſoever it may happen to coſt me for ſo doing. But I wave it, becauſe it ſeems to be a thing altogether unneceſſary to beſtow any Labour that way, where the caſe is ſo evident and notorious, that every one, I know, has already prevented me therein, and can eaſily make the Application himſelf, without any other help: And beſides, becauſe (to ſpeak ſincerely) I look upon this as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument far more fit for <hi>Tears</hi> than <hi>Speech.</hi> And therefore one thing only I ſhall venture to add, as to my own particular; which as (God be praiſed) I can ſay with much Truth, ſo I hope I may ſay it alſo, at this time, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Vanity; nor do I doubt, notwithſtanding the general Apoſtaſie, but that many others are able to ſay the ſame.—I thank God, I have been hitherto ſo happy, is that I have never delivered to you any Doctrin, but what I firſt both firmly believed, and endeavoured alſo, as well as I could, to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe my own ſefi. And this I affirm, with a more particular reſpect to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106193:22"/>
true Church of <hi>England</hi> Doctrin concerning Loyalty and Non-reſiſtance. Of which whatſoever has been lately ſaid, or done by ſome Men to the contrary, has ſerved only (if poſſible) ſtill more to confirm me in the Truth of my own Principles. And if, upon this very account, I muſt be at length ſo unhappy, as to be forced from my Place and Function, God's will be done. I hope I am prepared to bear this alſo (like all other meer Misfortunes) both Patiently and with Thanſgiving.</p>
            <p>And, indeed, if there were no more in the caſe than this, 'tis, I think, even high time to have done Preaching in that Place, where a Man can be no longer permitted to do ſo, but upon ſuch hard Conditions only, after the performance of which he cannot reaſonably expect to be ever any more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in what he ſays: Whilſt for my own part, I ſhall ever look upon this of my Text to be both true Goſpel and ſound Reaſon too: And ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be far from making any Queſtion of it, but that he <hi>Who teacheth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ought to teach himſelf alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And accordingly, I ſhall conclude all with that excellent Prayer in our Church Litany, which, I am confident, needs no mending, but would effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually ſerve to mend them, who may think it does, did they but as hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily make uſe of it, as I deſire you all to join with me therein at preſent.—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it pleaſe thee, O Lord, to illuminaue all Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, with true Knowledge and Underſtanding of thy Word, and grant, that both by their Preaching and Living, they may ſet it forth and ſhew it accordingly; and that thy Church, being always preſerved from falſe Teachers and Apoſtles, may be ordered and guided by faithful and true Paſtors, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Some of the more material Faults of the Preſs.</head>
            <p>PAge 12. line 10. for he ſpoken read he had ſpoken. p. 26 l. 28. f. that caſe r. the caſe. p. 28. l. 24. f. indifectible, than infallible to their Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as to their Manners; r. indifectible as to their Manners than infallible as to their Underſtandings. p. 29. l. 6. f. therefore r. therefrom.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
